Finding Aid for the Rowland Hill Harvey Papers LSC.0187
UCLA Library Special Collections
Rowland Hill Harvey papers
1909-1939
UCLA Library Special Collections
Harvey, Rowland Hill
LSC.0187
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Rowland Hill Harvey (1889-1943) was a social worker in Chicago and Los Angeles (1910-15), and later, an associate professor of history at UCLA. He wrote Samuel Gompers, Champion of the Toiling Masses (1935) and Robert Owen, Social Idealist (1949). The collection consists of manuscripts and printed material documenting Rowland Hill Harvey's publications and talks on American history.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917203953606533
Biography
Harvey was born on March 24, 1889 at Battle Creek, Iowa; social worker in Chicago and Los Angeles, 1910-15; BA (1918) and MA (1920), University of Southern California; Ph.D, Stanford University, 1923; instructor in history, University of Iowa, 1924; instructor in history (1924-25), assistant professor (1925-30), then associate professor, UCLA; wrote Samuel Gompers, Champion of the Toiling Masses (1935) and Robert Owen, Social Idealist (1949); he died on March 10, 1943.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts and printed material documenting Rowland Hill Harvey's publications and talks on American history. Includes copies of speeches and other research material on Samuel Gompers, as well as correspondence, clippings and other printed material related to Harvey's book, Samuel Gompers, Champion of the Toiling Masses (1935).
Gompers, Samuel; Harvey, Rowland Hill, 1889-1943--Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of History--Faculty -- Archives
- Carbon Copies of Speeches by Samuel Gompers, Including Extracts and Synopses
  - Cornell University., February 7, 1901. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typographical Temple, Catholic University., February 3, 1909. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New York University Forum., December 12, 1913.; 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mount Grappa, Italy., October 11, 1918. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Assumption Cemetary, Syracuse, New York., October 18, 1920. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Eulogy at grave of William Klopetsky.
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 29 W. 39th St., New York., November 5, 1920. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marquette Club, Plaza Hotel., February 16, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Washington Central Labor Union., March 31, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Moose Hall, Philadelphia., April 2, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academy of Music, Philadelphia., April 24, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Civic Center, Denver., June 16, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rotary Club, Denver., June 16, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carpenters Hall, Denver., June 25, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Victoria Cafe, Atlantic City., August 24, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Federation of Labor Building, Washington, D.C., October 31, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Montclair High School., December 4, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Caravan Club, Washington Hotel, Washington, D.C., December 16, 1921. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Otto Johansson Socialdemokraten Barnhusgatan 14, Stockholm, Sweden., March 1, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - City Club, Chicago., April 11, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Extract (Gomper's words) from minutes of Executive Council meeting, Washington, D.C., May 10-18, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - City Club of Cincinnati., June 9, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Civitan Club, Astor Hotel, New York., September 21, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ambassador Hotel, Atlantic City, New Jersey., September 16, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Remarks to executive council of American Federation of Labor.
  - 4th Annual Conference of American Legion, New Orleans., October 17, 1922. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lafayette Hotel, Washington D.C., Albert Thomas banquet., January 10, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - (?). Beethovan Hall fund-raising for German Trade Union Movement., February 18, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Words to be embodied in an address to the House of Representatives by Congressman Cooper at John I. Nolan Memorial Services., February 25, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Demonstration before Federation of Labor Bank, New York (Summary)., May 19, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dinner, Shelburne Hotel (extract)., May 19, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Continental Memorial Hall, Washington, D.C., May 24, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conference called by American Legion, Continental Memorial Hall., June 14, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oregon Press Club, Portland., October 4, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - City Hall, Astoria, Oregon., October 7, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Convention of American Legion, San Francisco., October 18, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - El Paso, Texas., October 26, 1923. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - International Order of Foresters, Court National 4321, Washington, D.C. (Synopsis)., March 4, 1924. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conference Board of Physicians in Industry, New York., April 4, 1924. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conference called by Governor Gifford Pinchot, the Capitol, Harrisburg., April 8, 1924. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Club Car, Golden State Limited, en route from Chicago to El Paso., November 11, 1924. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Printed Copies of Speeches etc. by Samuel Gompers
  - National Security League, Chicago., September 14, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lexington Avenue Theatre, New York City., February 22, 1918. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Why the Peace Treaty Should be Ratified. American Labor's Reasons for Supporting the League of Nations Convenant With its Labor Provisions., ca. 1918. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Labor and Antitrust Legislation. The Facts, Theory and Argument. A Brief and Appeal. addressed to members of the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Various newspapers containing articles on Gompers, 1917-1924.; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Account of proceedings at the National Cure Federation Headquarters, New York City, August 13, 1918.; (1 item, typed carbon copy). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American seamen and the war of 1917. Paper filed by Samuel Gompers...as part of his address to United States Navy War College, Newport, Rhode Island, April 18, 1922.; (1 item, typed carbon copy). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Drafts of(?) a radio speech on Gompers, Spring 1935.; 2 manuscripts, pencil. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, clippings and other printed material re Rowland Hill Harvey's biography of Gompers, Samuel Gompers, Champion of the Toiling Masses, 1933-1935. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes a copy of the official program for the dedication of the Gompers memorial monument in the Triangular Park, Washington, D.C., October 7, 1933.
  - Typed copies of book reviews of Harvey's biography of Gompers, 1935. (Box 1, Folder 10)